翻译 koki  放 晴  La Fatalité
Long, long ago, in the distant past,
遠い遠い遥かな昔
amidst the blind chaos,
無明の混沌の中に「始まりと終わりの管理者」と名乗る者が現れました
压制 暗之亚瑟王  校对 凉YAN Lucifer 时间 Lucifer
a being calling himself "the Overseer of
the Alpha and the Omega" appeared.
彼はまず最初に混沌から天と地と海を造りました
His first order of business was
creating the Heavens, the Earth,
and the oceans from the chaos.
Doing this took him one million years.
これには百万年かかりました
Then he molded and shaped the remaining
chaos into the animals and plants.
次に　残った混沌を固めて削り
動物と植物を造りました
This took...
これには…
A hundred thousand years!
十万年
Precisely.
如何にも
He also spent another ten thousand
years creating Man.
さらに一万年かけて人間たちを
Last, he divided his own body into thirds
そして最後に己の体を切り裂き三人の神様を作りました
and created three Deities.
He gave each of these three Gods a role
in watching over the world. These are...
世界を三つに分け管理をそれぞれ任せることに決めたのです
それが…
The overseer of life that is
yet to come, Orntorra!
「未だ来らざるものの管理者--オルントーラ」
The overseer of life that
now exists, Towitorra!
「現れあるものの管理者--トーイトーラ」
Exactly! Exactly!
如何にも　如何にも
そして最後に残った一人こそ…
And the remaining one is
the overseer of life that has passed,
過ぎ去りし者の管理者
the God who, eons and eons ago,
created our almighty Library...
遥か古にこの偉大なる図書館を作った神
The God of the past, Bantorra!
「過去神バントーラ」にございます
This is the final destination
for all life in the world.
すべての生の終着点--神立バントーラ図書館へようこそ
Ladies and gentlemen, I welcome
you to Bantorra Library.
Todomaru mono oroka narishi
止まる者　愚かなりし
はらりひらり指に触れた黒い翼の　一片
Harari hirari yubi ni fureta
kuroi tsubasa no hitohira
诸
神字幕组
君が一つの　物語なら
Kimi ga hitotsu no monogatari nara
まだいくらでも　掛け替えられる
Mada ikura demo kakikaerareru
Chi no inku wa kawakanai
血のインクは乾かない
Dare mo shiranai hontou no bokura
誰も知らない　本との僕ら
荒れた世界　枯れるのは
Areta sekai kaeru no wa
Oimotometa no wa
追い求めたのは　ちっぽけな幸福なんかじゃない
Chippoke na koufuku nanka ja nai
Tatakae todoroku kodou wo aizu ni
戦え　轟く　音を合図に
Inomama susumeba yukusaki hatenai
意のまま　進めば
行く先　果てない
Aragae notauchi ikudo to yaburedo
抗え　のたうち
幾度と　汚れと
Kizamou matotta kizuato ni yume wo
膝を纏った傷跡に夢を
埋もれそうな今日の記憶繋げるために　明日へ
Umoresou na kyo no kioku
tsunageru tame ni ashita e
Episode 2
Bombs, a Princess, and a Gray Town
第2话 爆弹与公主和灰色城市
すみません  通してください
Pardon me! Coming through!
Ah-ah-ah-ah...
The days we allow general admission
are so exhausting.
しんどいわね
一般開放日のこの時期は…
But the show must go on.
でも踏ん張らなきゃ…
Everyone's come so far to see us.
皆さん遥遥いらっしゃってるんだもの
They do say that the Armed Librarian
is the most difficult to enter
世界で一番就くのが難しい職業それが武装司書だと言われています
of all the world's vocations.
Let's see. Next is library four.
えーと…　次は第四書庫ね
Deaths from 1873...
1873年持つ…
What? That's like fifty years ago!
えー　五十年ものか
To defeat the monsters lurking in
the labyrinth beneath the annals
収蔵庫の地下迷宮に巣くう魔物たちを倒し
and have the strength to oversee the Books...
「本」を管理できる強さを持つ
These are the absolute requirements
for an Armed Librarian.
それが武装司書の絶対条件
And the one who currently
stands above us all...
そして現在　われわれの頂点に立つのが…
Acting Director Hamyuts Meseta, yes?
ハミュッツ＝メセタ　館長代行ね
No one can deny that she's strong,
確かにあの人は強い
but...
ですが…
But?
ですが？
あっ　いいえ
Never mind.
How about a scone?
スコーンでもいかが？
People's deaths are to be mourned.
人の死は悲しまなくてはならない
The ability to save people
should be celebrated.
救えることを喜ばなくてはならない
Life itself should be exalted.
人が生きることを喜ばなくては…
Volken...
ヴォルケン…
俺はアロン湾で己の信じる正義を貫けませんでした
In Aro Bay, I was unable to uphold
my personal ideals of justice.
Do I even have the right to call
myself an Armed Librarian?
この俺に武装司書を名乗る資格があるでしょうか？
Word came from Luimon, at Toatt Mine.
トアット鉱山のルイモンから定時連絡があった
They found another fragment of
the ever-laughing witch's Book.
「常笑いの魔女」の「本」の新たな破片　やはり現地で見つかったそうだ
Oh.
あー　そう
Someone's in a good mood today.
えらく上機嫌だな
Yeah. We can't wait to get some killing
and butchering done, can we, Bunny?
早いところぶっ殺したり　落ちんだりしたいわね　うさっちゃん
Can't you at least respond,
"You betcha!" or something?
そうだぴょんぐらい言ったら　付き合い悪いなぁ
You're a bad friend!
You're something else... You know that?
大した玉だよ　君は
I wonder what fun tricks they'll
send my way next...
次はどんな手で楽しませてくれるのかしら
My friend in the Church of Drowning
in God's Grace...
神溺教団の誰かさん？
This smoke is nasty.
You can barely see the sky.
ひどい煙だ
ろくに空も見えん
鉱山で石炭を燃やしてるせいだ
It's because of the coal they
burn in the mines.
Kill Hamyuts Meseta...
ハミュッツ＝メセタを殺せ
機械で土を掘って　「本」を探してる
They drill out the earth with machines,
searching for Books.
Kill Hamyuts Meseta...
Colio, have you ever read a Book?
コリオ　お前　「本」を読んだことは？
That's right. That was a Book.
そうだ　あれが「本」
Hey, guys! Interested in Books?
お兄さんたち　「本」に興味がないかい？
What about Book central, Toatt Mine?
「本」の名産地トアット土産に　どうだ？
Just yesterday, they dug
these out of the mine.
昨日掘り出したばっかりの「本」だ
They're all top-quality, sealed rarities.
どれもこれも超一級封印ものの貴重品だ
行くぞ
Let's go.
Ah, hold on!
よっ　待ちなぁよ
砕けた欠片ちょっとしか読めんねえが
I've got a broken fragment,
so you can only read a bit of it.
Since it's incomplete, I'll cut you a deal.
その分　安くしっとくぜ
What do you say?
どうだい？　ひとつ？
Back off.
かまうな
But the price...
You there!
そこの男
Bantorra Library forbids all
unauthorized Book sales.
「本」の勝手な売買は神立図書館の名において禁じられている
あっ　武装司書
An Armed Librarian!
ちょっと来い　話をきこうか
Come with me! I've got some
questions for you.
Pl-Please... Go easy on me!
ご、ご勘弁を
Hey, don't grip yourself too hard.
おい　あまり強く触るな
爆発するぞ
You'll detonate.
Give me a hand, Colio.
手を貸せ　コリオ
Kill Hamyuts Meseta...
ハミュッツ＝メセタを殺せ
Kill...
しっかりしろ　息をおせ
Relax. Try to breathe.
するんだな…爆発
We're going to explode soon, aren't we?
じゃ　早くハミュッツ＝メセタを見つけないと
Then we'd better hurry and
find Hamyuts Meseta.
You...
お前…
Oh? Not feeling well?
おやー　具合でも悪いですか
この町は空気が悪いからね
It's because of the nasty air in this town.
Do you think I could get a glass of water?
水を一杯もらえるか
それにパンとエールを二人分
Also, bread and ale for two.
Absolutely. That'll be one kirue each.
毎度あり　どっちも一キルヤです
You came to this town because
you're interested in Books?
この町には皆さん「本」にご興味があって？
You could say that.
まぁな…
やっぱり「本」って面白いものですよ
Books really are fascinating.
俺も大分前　一つ買わされましたよね
I got sold one once, a long time ago.
So then, my girlfriend and I...
で　うちの彼女と…
Shut up.
うるさい
Where's Hamyuts Meseta?
ハミュッツ＝メセタはどこにいる？
Wh-What's the big idea?
な…なによ？
Knock it off, Colio.
コリオ　止せ
ハミュッツ＝メセタの居場所を教えろ
Tell me where Hamyuts Meseta is.
教えるんだ！
Tell me or else.
As I thought.
やはり　そうだ
All three of you, take off your shirts.
三人ども　シャツを脱げ
An Armed Librarian.
武装司書
神溺教団の者だな
You're with the Church, aren't you?
What are you plotting here?
この町で何を企んでる？
Answer me!
答えろ！
Guilty!
有罪！
「常笑いの魔女」死刑にさす
The ever-laughing witch
shall be put to death!
まぁ　どうした？　おい
Hey, what's wrong? Hey!
A bladed attack? Where did it come from?
斬撃？
一体どこから…
ハミュッツ＝メセタを殺せ！
Kill...
Hamyuts Meseta!
ヒョウエ！
Hyoue!
Sir!
旦那
Stay back.
来るな！
Get the hell out of here!
逃げろ！
Come with me!
来い！
ふん　無様な
Pathetic.
Damn it. It happened again.
畜生　まただ…また助けられなかった
Yet again, I couldn't save someone.
Again?
また？
It's the same as when I
left my mother to die.
同じだ　御袋を見殺しにしたあの時と
Bombs fell from the sky.
空から爆弾が…
That time, too, I stood there, powerless.
あの時も　なにもできず
俺はどうすればいい？
What do I do?
Should I cry?
泣けばいいのか？
でも　ヒョウエのために泣けること… 俺はあいつを知らないんだ
But I didn't know Hyoue well
enough to cry for him.
We just met...
なんてことだ？　なにも…
Let's kill Hamyuts Meseta.
ハミュッツ＝メセタを殺そう
なに？
What?
We're the same as he was.
どうせ同じだ
この胸の爆弾でハミュッツを殺して俺たちも
We bear these bombs in our chests to
kill Hamyuts, and then we die too.
That's true, but...
そうだけとよ
Yes. We're not human. We're bombs.
そう　人間じゃない
爆弾　爆弾のために涙など…誰も…
Who would shed tears for a bomb...
Luimon...
ルイモンさん
Noloty, I'll give you until the sand
in this hourglass runs out
ノロティさん
後一回だけこの砂が下に落ちるまで泣くことを許します
to finish your crying.
済んだら仕事に戻るのよ
After that, you're going back to work.
I don't care if you're an apprentice.
見習いとは言え　武装司書に感傷は許されません
Armed Librarians are not allowed
emotional weakness!
Really? Luimon's dead?
そう　ルイモンが死んだの？
Yes.
はい
Well, he had it coming. Being that weak...
しょうがないわね　弱かったから
Director.
代行
I warned him that he wouldn't
last, as weak as he was.
そんな弱いなら続けられないよって言ったんだけどねぇ
I guess that's a lesson you don't
learn until you're dead.
やっぱそう言うのって死ななきゃ分からないものね
Well, well.
あら
Volken?
ヴォルケン
Director, take me with you!
代行　僕も一緒に
ミレポ　うちで一番皆殺しが上手なのは誰かしら？
Milepoc, who among us is
the best massacre artist?
代行です
You are, Director.
And who is the worst?
じゃ　一番苦手っ子ちゃんは？
君よ　ヴォルケン
It's you, Volken.
I don't need a child that balks
at the sight of dying Meats.
「肉」どもの死に動揺するような子どもはお断り
You're strong.
強さはある　知性も　適性も
You're smart and talented.
But you
けどあなたには…心がない
don't have a heart!
Volken...
ヴォルケン
Milepoc, what are your thoughts
on the forecast?
ミレポ
あの予報どう思う？
Forecast?
予報って？
今朝　魔道庁の予知魔法科に問い合わせたんだが
The one run by the Magic Bureau's
Predictions Division.
You mean those weathermen?
あの天気予報屋さんたち？
トアット鉱山一帯に台風が近づいていると答えが
They said a typhoon is approaching
the Toatt Mine area.
But there's no record of a storm hitting the
region within the past hundred years.
この百年間当地に嵐の記録はありません
That area is strongly aligned to the element of
earth. A typhoon hitting it would be...
あそこは強力な土属性の地域だし　台風の接近など…
Really? This is getting more
exciting by the minute.
ええ　ますます楽しみね
爆弾じゃない
I'm not a bomb.
I used to be a human...
人間だったはずだ　俺は
A bomb? Who did it?
爆弾？　なに　誰が？
The Armed Librarians are searching
like crazy for him, apparently.
武装司書の奴ら　しばらくで犯人を捜してるらしいぜ
And where might you be going, Relia?
どこへ行くつもりだね？
レーリア君？
You...
貴様が…
神溺教団とは一体なんだ？
What the hell is the Church
of Drowning in God's Grace?
Tell me,
答えろ　「真人」　シガル＝クルケッサ
True Man, Cigal Crekessa.
なぜ私の名を？
How do you know my name?
When the False Men captured and threw
me on the boat, they mentioned it.
「擬人」ともが話していた
俺を捕まえて　船に押し込める時
Surprising... You have memories from
before you became a Meat?
驚いたなぁ
「肉」になる前の記憶があるのか
ほんの少しでもなぁ
Only a few.
よかろ　一杯付き合いたまえ
Fine.
Join me for a drink.
武装司書が全力を挙げて取り締まっている禁断の邪教
We are of the heretic creed,
that which the Armed Librarians devote
full efforts toward stopping...
それがわれわれ
The Church of Drowning in God's Grace.
神溺教団
Precisely.
その通り　われわれの教義はただ一つ
Our doctrine espouses but one directive,
to actualize your every desire.
己の欲望をすべて肯定すること
Desire?
欲望？
Food, sex, fame...
食欲　色欲　名誉欲　支配欲に破壊欲
The desire to rule and the desire to destroy...
己が欲望を突き詰め真の幸福を体験したものだけが
And only those who embody the true happiness
found by fulfilling one's desires
will be granted entrance into
Heaven, upon death.
死後天国に迎え入れられる
They will become the ultimate Books.
究極の幸福な「本」となって
And the Armed Librarians don't like that.
武装司書どもはそれが面白くないのさ
They want to store all the world's
Books in a central library.
何しろ奴らはこの世のすべての「本」を図書館の管理科に納めたがっているのでね
But that's absurd. I will never
let them have my Book.
だが笑止　私の「本」は決して奴らに…
Why me?
なぜ俺を…なぜ俺を爆弾に改造した？
Why did you turn me into a bomb?
ふん　「肉」にしては少し増しかとを思えば
I thought you were a little
smarter than the usual Meat...
Yet you don't even know that?
そんなことすら分からんとは…
I'm a True Man.
私は「真人」
We're the upper echelon of the Church,
and we will embody true happiness.
真の幸福を体験する教団でもっとも尊いぐらいな者だ
The False Men are those
who do our dirty work.
その手足となって働くのが「擬人」
And then...
そして　君たちは「肉」
There's your kind, the Meat.
You aren't human. You're
disposable, like cattle.
人ですらない使い捨ての家畜だ
You should feel honored to help me,
Cigal Crekessa, find happiness.
光栄に思えたまえ
このシガル＝クルケッサの幸福のために
なるほど
I knew it.
I knew I hadn't been human for a long time.
確かに俺は　特に人間じゃなくなっていたようだ
Great.
結構　では仲間のもとに戻って　己の務めを果たすがいい
Now return to your fellow Meats.
Do your job.
Yes, that's exactly what I'll do.
あ　そうさせてもらう
Rot in Hell, Cigal.
あばよ　シガル　これが俺の務めだ
This is my job!
Another bomb?!
また爆弾？
This town's gone to hell in a handbasket.
どうなっちまったんだ　この町は
ふん　「肉」の分際で敵前逃亡とは
I can't let a lowly Meat escape before the enemy.
いかんよ
有罪
Guilty!
Did Relia escape?
レーリアの奴　逃げたのか？
Even if we escape, a bomb
can never become human.
逃げても爆弾　人間にはなれない
Humans are...
人間とは…
I'm done.
もう無理だ
I guess you really can be all cried out...
涙が出尽くす　ほんとにあるのね
好きな人が死んだら　ほかにどうすればいいのかしら
What else is there to do when
the person you love dies?
あのさ　君に話しかけてるんよ
Hey, I'm talking to you.
You're weird.
変な人　名前は？
What's your name? I'm la Mira.
あたし　イア＝ミラ
Um, the person who died...
その　死んだ人は　その死んだ人は人間だったのか？
Was the person who died human?
Of course.
当たり前でしょう　カートヘロ＝マシュウって言ってね
His name was Kartohero Mashear.
He sold bread by the side of the road.
道ばたでパンを売ってたの
でも　昨日の爆弾事件で
But in the explosion yesterday...
最初に惚れたのは私のほうでさ
I was the one who fell for him.
ね　あなたはしたことある？
Hey, have you ever fallen
in love at first sight?
一目ぼれ
You really are a weird person.
本当に変な人
I'm not a person. I'm...
人じゃない　僕は…
But I feel a little better now. Thank you.
でも少し楽になった　ありがとう
Director, it's in sight,
代行　見えました　トアット鉱山です
the Toatt Mine.
Okay, then I'm counting on you two.
じゃ　宜しくね　二人とも
You be careful, too, Director.
代行こそ　お気をつけて
Godspeed.
ご武運を
はいはい
Yeah, yeah.
Kill Hamyuts Meseta.
ハミュッツ＝メセタを殺せ
Kill Hamyuts Mese...
ハミュッツ＝メセ…
A Book...
「本」　あの男か？
Could this be his?
さって　お立会い
Okay, watch and observe.
I shall pull an adorable
rabbit out of this hat.
この中より　見事可愛い兎が出てきましたら
S-Sorry about that.
こ、これは失礼　因みにあれは「三毛猫」
By the way, that was a calico cat.
私三毛ボン
Call me Calico.
Meow!
みゃあん
ねえ　少しは楽になった？
So, do you feel a little better?
Yeah. Thanks.
うん　ありがとう
It's going to itch for a while,
but don't scratch it.
しばらく痒くなるけど　帰っちゃだめ
Also, promise me that no matter
how much it hurts,
後　どんなに苦しくても明日の朝まで水は飲まないで
you won't drink any water
until tomorrow morning.
約束よ
Okay.
うん　でも　お姉ちゃん一体誰なの？
But... Miss, who are you?
私は　ごめんね
I'm...
Sorry.
Oh, here you are...
ほや　こちらにいらっしゃいましたか？
The nation's saint, the ever-laughing witch.
「救国の聖女」　「常笑いの魔女」様
Wyzaf...
ワイザフ
That girl...
あの人…
Why are you running, Colio?
コリオ　なぜ走る？
分からない
I don't know.
Why do you run?
なぜ走る　お前が
You're a...
...bomb, aren't you?
爆弾だろ
You're a bomb, aren't you?
I am. But...
そうだ　けど…
I have to save that girl.
助けなきゃ　あの子を
Because she's...
だって　あの子　人間だ
human!
いない
She's not here.
What is that?
なんだ？　あれ
Shall we get this show on the road?
早速始まりますか　手早くね
Quickly.
Kill Hamyuts Meseta.
ハミュッツ＝メセタを殺せ
Found the first one!
一人目　見っけ
Bingo! One down!
ビンゴ　まずは一人
Next!
さあ　次ぎ
Oh, she's here at last.
ついに現れたか　いいぞ
Excellent.
Kill Hamyuts Meseta.
ハミュッツ＝メセタを殺せ
It's beautiful.
きれいだ
見つけた
Found ya!
Taiyo tojiru mae ni
Hikari wo nakushite
Mekurumeku arashi nara
Temaneku mae ni tobikomu
Dare mo itsuka owaru no deshou
Sono hi ga kureba
Mawaridasu mirai wo mezashite
Tada sore wa mou shirusarete ita to shitemo
Sagashidasu kizutsuku imi sae kono te ni
Jibunrashiku aru tame ni
A Bomb,
The Church's plot wraps around your toes.
爪先に絡みつく神溺教団の企み
A Bomb, Humans,
The Church's plot wraps around your toes.
Run. Run for dear life, boy.
走れ　逃げろ　少年
やって来るぞ　ハミュッツ＝メセタ
She's coming...
A Bomb, Humans, Death, and God's Sickness
爆弹与人类和死神之疾
Hamyuts Meseta.